Guide to the NSF/CEME Decentralization Conference Records, 1961-1996 RL.11405
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
NSF/CEME Decentralization Conference Records
1961-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
NSF/CEME Decentralization Conference
RL.11405
3 Linear Feet
55 Megabytes
The NSF/CEME Decentralization Conference seminars are funded by a grant from the National Science Foundation (NSF) and administered through the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER). This collection includes materials relating to the planning and programming of the Decentralization Conferences during Roy Radner's tenure as coordinator.
Biographical / Historical
The Decentralization Conference-Seminars are funded by a grant from the National Science Foundation (NSF) and administered through the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER). The CEME, Conferences on Econometrics and Mathematical Economics, was created to form several series of standing national seminars on various topics. Both the General Equilibrium and Decentralization conference series were formed out of the mathematical economics side of the organization. The Decentralization Conference was first coordinated by Roy Radner. The conference is traditionally held once a year, but occasionally more often. The first Decentralization Conference was held at UC Berkeley in 1971.
The term decentralization refers to the starting point of many of the problems addressed in the series: the necessary information starts in a decentralized state. Much of the conference series has focused on questions of design and of various systems for production and allocation of goods, services, and information. These range from understanding voting systems to markets to the organization of the internal lines of communication and assignment of tasks within a firm. Topics covered at past conferences include: mechanism and market design, recourse allocation, matching, team theory, contracting, organization of the firm, communication, computation, and processing of information. Currently, the Decentralization conference series includes the design of any institutions, contracts, organizations, or relationships in which information and/or incentives play a role.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, except Accession 2017-0040 also included 55 megabytes of digital records that are closed pending processing.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Decentralization Conference Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift of Theodore Groves in 2017.
Collection Overview
Most of the NSF/CEME Decentralization Conference Records are from Roy Radner’s tenure as coordinator (1961-1996). Paper records been divided into two series, Conferences and Seminars, and Administrative Files. Conferences and Seminars consists of programs, correspondence, conference papers and abstracts, notes, memos, planning documents, reports, and survey responses. Most of the documents are from the Decentralization conferences and seminars spanning the years 1971-1996; these are arranged alphabetically by conference title, and chronologically by year within each conference. The Administrative Files series includes documents more generally pertaining to the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER) and National Science Foundation (NSF), such as correspondence, annual reports, and memoranda. This series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Accession 2017-0040 also includes 55 megabytes of digital records that are closed pending processing.
Econometrics; Economics, Mathematical; Economics -- Research; Decentralization in government; Radner, Roy, 1927-; National Bureau of Economic Research; National Science Foundation (U.S.)
- Conferences and Seminars, 1971-1996; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Conferences and Seminars consists of programs, correspondence, conference papers and abstracts, notes, memos, planning documents, reports, and survey responses. Most of the documents are from the Decentralization conferences and seminars spanning the years 1971-1996. Also included are a handful of conferences sponsored by the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER) and National Science Foundation (NSF), such as the Conference on Decision Rules & Uncertainty, Conference-Seminar on the Theory of General Economic Equilibrium, Conference on Theoretical Industrial Organization, and the Seminar on Bayesian Inference in Econometrics. Arranged alphabetically by conference title, and chronologically by year within each conference.
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1971 February; 3 folders (Box 1)
    Planning and programming documents, correspondence, conference papers
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1971 June; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Correspondence, conference papers
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1972 February (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence, conference papers
  - Decentralization Conference Seminar, 1972 June; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Programs summary reports, conference papers
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1973 (Box 1)
    Correspondence, notes, conference papers
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    Planning documents for 1974 conference
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1974; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Decentralization Conference, 1974-1975; 4 folders (Box 1)
    Correspondence, conference papers, list of participants, survey responses, steering committee meeting minutes for 1975 conference
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1976 (Box 1)
    Program, conference papers
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence, conference papers, steering committee memos and notes
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1978 (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence, rapporteur's report, notes
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1979; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence, rapporteur's report, notes, memos
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1980; 6 folders (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence, conference papers, list of participants, survey responses, notes
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1981; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Correspondence, rapporteur's report
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1982; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence, reports
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1985; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Program, correspondence
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1986 (Box 2)
    Program, correspondence, conference papers, notes
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1987 (Box 2)
    Program, correspondence, conference paper
  - Decentralization Seminar, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
    Programs, correspondence, notes
  - Decentralization Conference, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Decentralization Conference, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Microeconomics Workshop, 1987 (Box 2)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Conference on the Analysis of Consumer Expenditure Data, 1974 (Box 2)
    Program
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Conference on Decision Rules & Uncertainty, 1974 (Box 2)
    Conference papers
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Conference on Education as an Industry, 1971 (Box 2)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Conference-Seminar on the Theory of General Economic Equilibrium, 1975 (Box 2)
    Correspondence, conference paper abstracts
  - National Science Foundation Conference on Theoretical Industrial Organization, 1976 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Seminar on Bayesian Inference in Econometrics, 1976 (Box 2)
- Administrative Files, 1961-1995; 2
  Administrative Files consists of documents more generally pertaining to the National Bureau of Economic Research, National Science Foundation, and Office of Naval Research. Documents include correspondence, annual reports, and memoranda. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Memoranda, 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Planning Documents, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    Program, participants, and notes from previous meetings
  - National Bureau of Economic Research Expense Forms, 1980 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation Grant, 1976-1981; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Correspondence, reports
  - Office of Naval Research Final Report and Inventory of Research, 1961-1971; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Annual and summary reports
  - Assorted articles, 1994-1995; 3 folders (Box 2)